In this lesson, we are going to be looking at two special keywords in Python and in a whole lot of
other programming languages called Break and Continue.
These are important when it comes to loops.
So I'm going to give you a another example of a for loop that we have already seen.
So let's just write a normal one for a variable I in range.
Let's just keep it really simple in range ten print.
Ah.
And just in case you have forgotten.
It does that which well, you shouldn't have forgotten.
So I'm not even going to explain that.
I'm sure you know why it has done that.
If you've forgotten, you can go back to our lessons that we covered this in lots of detail.
Yes.
Okay.
So that's what it does.
But now let's just say we don't want it to print five for some reason, which doesn't really make much
sense here, but it does play an important role in a lot of circumstances.
So let's say we don't like fire for some reason.
We just don't want five to be printed out.
The way you do that is you use the keyword continue.
So in order to tell the loop we don't want five, we're going to actually have to use an if statement.
So if you remember if statements help you make decisions.
So if I is equal to remember the double equal five, then what I'm going to say is continue.
Okay.
So let's see what that does.
And then obviously this print are still here.
But notice the print ah is not indented.
So that means it's not in this if statement.
And again also remember you'll see this if and the print is actually well they also have an indentation
because they are inside this for loop.
So because the if and the print have one indentation away from this beginning of the for loop.
They are inside the for loop, and then this one has one indentation away from the if it's inside the
if so, you can kind of see it logically that what is inside of what.
And just remember that obviously those indentations are very important anyways.
So let's just run that program.
And now you'll see if we counted from the beginning 012346 and that five is gone.
Because that is exactly what continue is doing.
So what continue is actually done is it's gone.
Okay.
For I in range ten started 0123.
So on when it gets to five.
So I is not equal to five.
If I is equal to five yes it is.
Continue.
So what continue does is it ignores everything else inside the for loop below it.
It just brings you or brings the program straight back to the top here.
So as soon as the continue is encountered, it just goes straight to the top.
And again are now becomes six and it carries on going.
So because continue brings you straight here.
It never got to that print statement for the five.
But if I had for instance put my print statement above this if.
You'll see that it now does print the fav.
And that's because it's obviously come in here.
And like we told you, it reads from top to bottom.
It's printed the ah okay.
If I is equal to five continue.
But there's nothing below that it's actually skipping out on.
So it's just now going to the top and it didn't really make any difference.
But let's bring it back to how it was.
And that will work.
Okay.
And now the other keyword I told you we have is break.
So what break does.
Is it basically does exactly what it says.
Let me run it for you to see.
Okay.
So now instead of saying, okay, continue to the top of the loop, we actually if you encounter that,
that means the loop is over.
We don't actually want to go any further further than that.
So even though we've told it, we want it to run ten times.
When I got to five, it came in here and said, okay, is I equal to five?
Yes, it is break.
And obviously it never got to that print statement.
So it never printed it over here.
So over here you could think, well why didn't we just make that five.
Well yes, we actually could have done that and then it wouldn't have printed the five.
So we could have actually just changed this range to saying four and range five, and it would have
done the exact same thing.
But again, this example break isn't that important, but in others it will be.
So that's just so now you know what continue does what break does.
And now that you know that, I'm going to try and test you with a bit of a more tricky example.
So this might look a bit confusing.
But everything we're doing in here, we have actually talked to you before.
So if you don't fully understand something of course you can always go back to that lecture, listen
to it again, and then come back to this.
And if you can understand this, then you know you really are in a good spot and you are on the right
track.
So let's get into it.
So what I'm going to do now is instead of doing a loop like that with numbers, we're going to write
a mini program where the user has to input a sentence.
And what our program is going to do is it's going to find all the vowels in the sentence and print those
and leave out the consonants.
So let's get into that.
So to do that first we're going to need a string with our vowels in.
So let's just call this string vowels.
We don't have to set this equal to the vowels.
And hopefully you remember what your vowels are.
What are they?
A e I o u.
Excellent.
Okay.
Hopefully you remembered those.
Okay, so we have our string with our vowels in it.
Then we're going to have another string.
Let's just call it sin short for sentence.
And remember we said we want the user to input a sentence so they can input whatever they want.
So we're just going to tell them input a sentence.
Okay.
Oh okay.
And put a sentence.
Okay.
Now this is where it starts to get a bit interesting and where you can see how these keywords are quite
useful.
So again, we're going to have a for loop and we are going to have a string based for loop.
So if you remember how to do that we have for a variable I in C.
So what we're doing here is again remember how before we just had this as a sentence maybe it was could
be hello whatever any string.
Um, but instead of now actually having a string here, we've just told the user to input it.
So it's, it's the same thing.
This variable just becomes whatever string the user inputs.
So for R in that sentence now we need an if statement again if.
I is not in vowels.
Okay.
That might look a little bit weird.
But basically what this is saying is it's getting I which will obviously be the first letter.
Well, to start with, it will be the first letter of the sentence the user has inputted.
And I'm going to run this all and go through it with you.
But for now, see if you can try.
Follow along.
I'm going to start with being the first letter of the sentence the user has inputted in.
So let's just say I typed in hello.
So I'm going to start off with being h if h, which is the first letter in are in, which is the first
letter in our sentence which I is holding is not inside vowels, then continue.
So if I if our variable I, whatever it is holding is not in our vowel, so it's not equal to a, e,
I, o, u.
In other words, then keep on going, because remember we want this program to only print vowels.
So obviously if our letter is not a vowel, because continue just then will bring us back to the top
of our program, and it will not see this print statement that we are writing down here where we're
saying print out.
So I'm going to run it and let's see exactly what happens.
Okay.
So I'm going to type hello.
because that's what I used earlier.
And what you'll see is I tapped E and I tapped o, which are obviously vowels.
So again what I was saying earlier is it came out.
Loop started and it started off with I equaling to this h here.
So if h is not in vowels continue is h in vowels.
Nope it's not.
So it skipped it and went back to the top.
Then it encountered E.
So this I over here became E.
If e is not in, vowels continue, but e is in vowels.
So this if statement is false.
So it didn't ever go inside here.
It never saw the continue instead, because this is false, it just went straight to the printer and
printed the E and it carried on along and along and obviously didn't print the L and didn't print that
L and didn't print.
And then eventually printed the O.
So, I mean, you can write whatever you want.
So it's a fun little program, but you can see how powerful now the for statement can be when we start
to put ifs and fours together.
And so we've now created a very clever program that you can quickly extract the vowels, if that's something
that you find handy and you need to do on a daily basis.
And just if you maybe decided or actually I'd rather have the consonants just take away that knot.
And now if I type that same sentence hello, it's now not giving me the vowels, because what I've said
here is I'm saying if I isn't vowels, then continue.
So as soon as it encountered that vowel over there, it wasn't vowel.
So it continued and it skipped this print down here.
So yeah, again, play around with it.
With programming you learn through practice and trying and just, you know, trying out new things.
So hopefully you understand this and uh, it all makes sense.
But yeah, I hope you understand more about for loops and while loops and of course this breaking continue
can be used in while loops as well.
And we will give that as an extra question in one of the quizzes.
So make sure you're doing those as well.